Guide to the Ruth Orkin Photograph Collection ca. 1950-1981 PR 190
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Ruth Orkin Photograph Collection
ca. 1950-1981
PR 190
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.83 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Ruth Orkin Photograph Collection spans the period from ca. 1950 to 1981 and contains photographs of New York City, primarily Central Park and the surrounding areas.
Provenance
Gift of Ruth Orkin, 1982
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Ruth Orkin is a photographer and filmmaker in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Ruth Orkin Photograph Collection spans the period from ca. 1950 to 1981 and contains photographs of New York City, primarily Central Park and the surrounding areas.
Photographs in this collection are part of a series taken from the window of Orkin's fifteenth floor apartment at 65 Central Park West, between 66th and 67th Streets in Manhattan; most were published at her books "A World through my Window," and "More Pictures from my Window." They take as their focus Central Park, particularly the Sheep Meadow, and the bordering skylines of Central Park South and Fifth Avenue. The color photographs show the park and its surroundings in various dramatic light, weather, and seasonal conditions, from the Tavern on the Green decorated with Christmas lights in a night view, to a distant shot of sunbathers and roller skaters gathered in the meadow in the heat of a summer day.
Most of the photographs in this collection were included in the exhibit "Manhattan Observed: Fourteen Photographers look at New York, 1972-1981," at the New-York Historical Society, from July 1981 through April 1982. The photographs, which were printed by G.W. Color Lab, New York, are signed, captioned, and in most cases dated by Orkin on both the front and the verso.
Central Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints
  - Unmatted
    - Tavern-on-the-Green, Holiday lights and 5th Ave., 1976 (Box 1)
    - Central Park South, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Sunlit Streets Over the East Sixties, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Moon Over August Concert, N.Y. Philharmonic in Sheep Meadow, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Peach Mist Over Sheep Meadow, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Rainbow Over 5th Ave., 1979 (Box 1)
    - Rosy City at Christmas, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Autumn and the Plaza Area, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Sheep Meadow, Central Park, 1980 (Box 1)
    - White, Feathery Trees, Central Park South, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Matted
    - Central Park South, Ca. 1950-1959 (Box 1)
    - White Light Over Central Park South and 5th Ave., 1972 (Box 1)
    - The Plaza With a Golden Roof, 1976 (Box 1)
    - The Plaza and Baseball in Summer, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Rainbow Over Hotel Carlyle, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Citycorp and the Plaza, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Black Glass Building at Sunset, E. 66th St., [ca. 1980] (Box 2)
    - Blue Sunrise Over Sheep Meadow, [ca. 1980] (Box 2)
    - Sheep Meadow After Re-sodding, 1981 May (Box 2)
    - Sunbathers and Roller-skaters, Sheep Meadow, 1981 (Box 2)